Sleigh Beggy.
（灰の目）
夜の愛し仔(スレイ･ベガ)
Dear child, with the name of a neighbor of long ago.
古き隣人の名を持つ愛しい子よ
A being nearer to us than the humans,
bearing a burden too great for a human child.
（灰の目）
人よりも我らに近しく
人の子では背負いきれぬ定めを
負う者よ
（灰の目）
ああ… まっこと かわいらしい
How adorable you are.
What will you find at the end of
your journey with the failure born
お前が森の影から生まれた
なり損ないと共に歩く先に
in the shadows of the forest?
何があるのか
Show me what you find.
（灰の目）
我に それを
見せておくれ
Where do those scars lie within your chest?
sono kizu wa mune no doko ni arimasu ka?
Can you hear my voice somewhere inside your heart?
kono koe wa kokoro no dokoka de kikoeteimasu ka?
When your scars and mine join together...
sono kizu to kono kizu wo kasaneta nara
When my voice and yours resound together...
kono koe to sono koe wo hibikaseta nara
Our intensity, hot tears, and bashful smiles...
hageshisa atsui namida hazukashisou na hohoemi
I used to think nothing of them, but now,
anna ni mo nanimo nai tte omoeteta watashi kara
So many unstoppable feelings are overflowing!
afuredasu yo konna ni mo tomedo nai kanjou ga ima
You're the one who finds yourself.
kimi ga kimi wo mitsukedasu
You're the one who saves yourself.
kimi ga kimi wo sukuidasu
So much is wrong and everyone breaks into a run.
machigai darake de daremo ga hashiridasu
You're the one who lives your own life,
kimi ga kimi wo ikite yuku
Trembling, hesitating all the while
furue nagara, tomadoi nagara
In a world where you're never truly alone.
hitori kiri janai sekai
But you're the only one of you there is!
dakedo kimi wa tatta ichi nin kimi shika inai
（綿蟲(わたむし)たち）メエ〜 メエ〜
Those are wooly bugs.
（エリアス）こいつらは綿蟲
Elias.
（チセ）エリアス
They consume the cold in the air and
grow fleece on their bodies, like sheep.
（エリアス）
空気中の冷気を食べて
羊に似た毛を生やすんだ
That means they multiply during the summer.
性質上 夏に増える
けど…
There are a lot this year, though.
今年は多いね
Are they neighbors?
（チセ）お隣さんですか？
No, they're closer to animals.
（エリアス）
いや どちらかといえば 生物寄り
Although very few humans can see them.
ほとんどの人間には
見つけられないけどね
Now, let's begin.
（エリアス）さあ 始めようか
（チセ）はい…
Okay.
（エリアス）
そうそう うまい うまい
That's it.
You're good at this.
Their wool is perfect for
using in magic and sorcery tools.
こいつらの綿は
魔法や魔術に関係した道具を
作るのに適していてね
Angelica asks me to do this, too.
アンジェリカからも
いつも頼まれてるんだ
Wow.
（チセ）へえ…
You can use the leftovers to make a pillow or something.
（エリアス）
余ったら 枕にでもするといい
You'll probably sleep well.
多分 よく眠れる
You might get to have the dreams you want to have.
見たい夢を
見たりできるかもしれないね
The dreams I want to have?
見たい夢…
終わったら
ちょっとだけ もらいます
I'll take a little when we're done.
Right.
あっ 手足は残して
胴体だけね
Oh, don't trim from their limbs. Just the torso.
Sorry. You could have told me sooner.
（チセ）
すみません
早めに言ってくれると…
（綿蟲たち）メエ〜 メエ〜
（エリアス）すごい量だな
That's quite a haul.
I'll go get a bag.
ちょっと 袋を持ってくるよ
You keep practicing.
チセは練習してて
（エリアス）そうだ
Oh, right.
はい
Yes?
If you find one that seems a bit
different, tell me before you touch it.
（エリアス）
少し違う蟲がいたら
触る前に僕に教えてね
はい
Okay.
（綿蟲）ピィー
I was going to talk to him as soon as I got home.
（チセ）
帰ったら すぐ
話をしようと思ったのに…
I don't know when I should bring it up.
どのタイミングで話せばいいのか
No, it's that I don't know what to tell him.
いや そもそも
何を話せばいいのか分からなく…
Timing...
タイミング… タイミング…
（ルツ）フン
No?
（チセ）
ダメか… 厳しい
He's so strict.
Has it always been so hard to talk?
話すのって
こんなに難しかったかな
It's different from the others.
（チセ）
ほかのと何か違う…
Ruth, look.
（チセ）ルツ あれ…
（ルツ）ん〜？
チセ！
Chise!
What is this thing?
なに これ？ 冷たっ…
It's so cold.
ハア…
Elias said to get him before I touch it.
（チセ）
エリアスは 触る前にって言ってた
What happens if I touch it first?
触ったら 何か…
この！
You little...
Shoot, it didn't work.
（チセ）
ダメだ 効いて…
（ルツ）チセ！
Chise!
Fire doesn't work, either.
（ルツ）火もダメか
A baby?
（チセ）
子供？
エリアス！
Elias.
You're done breeding.
（エリアス）
繁殖はできただろう　野に去れ
Go back to the fields.
Chise.
（エリアス）チセ
（ルツ）エリアス 何だ？ あれは
Elias, what was that?
A snow bug. Unlike wooly bugs, they eat warmth.
（エリアス）雪蟲(ゆきむし)だ
綿蟲と違って あれは暖気を食べる
It took her heat.
体の熱を食われたんだ
I'm sorry.
（チセ）ごめん… なさい
Chise didn't touch it.
（ルツ）チセは触らなかったぞ
あいつが突っ込んできた
It charged at her.
I know.
（エリアス）分かってる
It must have been hungry, since
summer is their breeding season.
夏の繁殖期で
腹が減ってたんだろう
We need to warm her up.
とにかく 温めなきゃ
Eli... as...
エリ… アス
Are you all right?
（エリアス）大丈夫？
（チセ）あ… だいぶ あったかく…
I'm quite a bit warmer.
It's actually too hot.
ていうか 暑いです
Where's Ruth?
ルツは？
He went to check on the snow bugs.
（エリアス）
雪蟲を見回りに行ったよ
（綿蟲たち）ピィー
Thank you.
ありがとうございました
今 どきます
I'll get out of the way.
Elias?
エリアス？
（エリアス）
君がいないときは寒かったけど
It was cold when you were gone.
But it's warm with you here.
こうしていたら 温かかった
I wonder why.
なんでだろう？
Uh...
えっと それは…
Well...
Chise...
（エリアス）チセ
（チセ）
タイミング…
Timing...
Chise, how was the land of dragons?
（エリアス）チセ
（チセ）あっ…
（エリアス）
ドラゴンの国は どうだった？
Uh, it was... well...
（チセ）あ… えっと その…
It was fun.
面白かったです
（エリアス）そっか
Yeah?
There was a huge snake-like
dragon in the river, dancing elves,
（チセ）
川にいる
蛇みたいな大きいドラゴンとか
踊るエルフとか 魔法で咲く花とか
and flowers that bloom with magic.
Yeah? That's good.
（エリアス）そう よかった
Lindel-san told me a lot, too.
リンデルさんからも
たくさん話を聞きました
So did Nevin.
ネヴィンとも
Nevin?
（エリアス）ネヴィンと？
２人とも
たくさん背中を押してくれました
They both gave me a lot of encouragement.
Elias, did I look tasty?
エリアス
私は おいしそうでしたか？
Oh, I mean...
あっ その…
（エリアス）起きてたのか
You were awake?
I thought it was a dream
until Lindel-san told me about it.
（チセ）
リンデルさんに聞くまで
夢だと思ってました
でも 単純に…
But I was just curious.
エリアス？
Elias?
Eli—
（チセ）エリ…
（エリアス）チセ
Chise, that's a memory that you don't need.
（エリアス）
それは 君には いらない記憶だ
Understood?
いいね？
嫌です
No.
I-It's about someone important to me!
だ… 大事なヒトのことなので！
いらなく… ないです
I do need it.
I-Impulse is a scary thing.
（チセ）
い… 勢いって怖い
You're really not scared of me, Chise?
（エリアス）
チセは本当に怖くないの？
僕のこと
You seem to think I'm really afraid of you.
あなたは
やけに 私が あなたを怖がると
思ってるみたいですけど
（エリアス）だって 僕は…
Am I not scary to a human?
人間から見たら
怖いんじゃないの？
I used to have family.
私には家族がいました
A mom, a dad, and a younger
brother who was still very little.
母と父と
弟は まだ小さくて…
Mom and Dad both had the sight.
父と母も視(み)える人で
２人とも すごく仲が良くて
They were really close to each other.
I was always terrified of the
scary things that swarmed toward us.
いつも 人でないものが
たくさん寄ってきて怖かったけど
でも 父がいるときには安全でした
But I was always safe with my dad around.
だけど…
But,
my dad vanished with my brother.
（チセ）
父が弟を連れて姿を消して…
I think my mom was tired.
母は疲れたんだと思います
So...
だから…
（チセ）
私を置いて 逝ってしまった
She left me and passed away.
私は家族が大好きで
I loved my family,
でも
私は連れていってもらえなくて
but they didn't take me with them.
So, I didn't want a family anymore.
だから
もう家族は欲しくなかった…
はずで
And yet...
Yet, you called me family.
だけど あなたが私を家族だって
（チセ）
彼が話す未来には いつも私がいて
The future he spoke of always involved me.
So I let myself think that we had a future together.
だから 私と彼には
先があるんだと思えてしまった
I wanted to learn about my family,
（チセ）
家族のことなら知りたいって
思えて…
but you wouldn't tell me anything.
でも あなたは
何もしゃべってくれないから
So when Lindel-san told me about your past,
だから リンデルさんが
昔のエリアスを教えてくれたときは
うれしかった
I was happy.
Happy?
（エリアス）うれしい？
It's not you that I'm afraid of.
私が怖いのは エリアスじゃなくて
It's you letting go of me.
あなたから
手を離されることなんですよ
Humans lie.
（エリアス）人間は うそをつく
I can't deny that.
それは否定のしようがない
（エリアス）でも…
But...
I'll believe in you.
チセは信じるよ
You're my apprentice, after all.
僕の弟子だからね
（エリアス）ねえ チセ
Say, Chise,
how does one feel when they care for another?
どう感じたら
人は他人を大事だと思うんだ？
How can you tell?
どうやって気付くの？
（チセ）う… それは…
Well...
As I've said before, I can't empathize.
（エリアス）
僕は 前にも言ったけど
共感ができない
So even if I wanted to say to you
what you said to me, I would be lying.
だから
君に同じ言葉を返したくても
うそになる
I...
僕は…
君がいないとき ひどく寒かった
I was terribly cold when you were gone.
What would you call that, in your words?
それは チセの言葉なら
何て言うんだろう？
（チセ）“さみしい”でしょうか
Loneliness, maybe?
I see.
（エリアス）そっか…
I was lonely.
僕は
〝さみしかった〞のか
He really is just a child.
（チセ）
やっぱり
このヒトは子供のままなんだ
A child that ended up in an adult's body.
そのまま大きくなってしまった
（エリアス）
やっぱり 君を買ってよかった
I'm glad I bought you.
Now I understand something new.
分かることが１つ増えた
じゃあ 人間のことに関しては
私が先生ですね
Then I guess I'm your teacher
when it comes to human things.
That sounds good.
（エリアス）それもいいね
改めて これからもよろしく
I look forward to learning from you,
人間の先生
teacher of human things.
こちらこそ 魔法の先生
Likewise, teacher of magic.
Speaking of which, I hadn't
gotten a good look at your wand.
（エリアス）
そういえば 君の杖を
しっかり見てなかった
Can you show it to me?
見せてくれる？
（チセ）どうぞ
Here.
（エリアス）
うん チセの髪と同じ色だ
It's the same color as your hair.
Though I was planning on finishing it.
本当は
僕が仕上げようと思ったんだけど
Is someone else supposed to do the finishing?
仕上げは
別の人がやるものなんですか？
We also use our wands to
help us along on our long journey.
（エリアス）
杖というのは
長い旅路を歩き通す
ためのものでもあるから
The seniors bless the wands of the youth
so that they can continue their journey.
若い同胞が きちんと
歩いていけるように
先達が若者の杖に
祝福するんだよ
Then if there ever comes a time
to make a second one, I'll ask you.
（チセ）
じゃあ
いつか２本目を作るときが来たら
エリアスに お願いしますね
I won't be in a hurry.
（エリアス）気長に待つよ
What are you doing this afternoon?
午後は どうするの？
（チセ）
そうですね…
魔法の勉強をしようかと
Let's see...
I think I'll study magic.
（エリアス）そう
Okay.
He still won't talk to me about himself.
（チセ）
結局 ほとんど自分のことは
話してくれないんだよな
Was there anything new while I was gone?
（チセ）
私がいない間
何か変わったことありましたか？
（エリアス）
いや
鳥が遊びに来たぐらいしかないね
Not really. Maybe a few birds that came to play.
Migratory birds or something?
（チセ）渡り鳥か何かですか？
I would have liked to see that.
ちょっと見たかったです
あ… あのときの
This is from back then.
Hm?
（チセ）ううん 何でもない
No, it's nothing.
I should get to studying first.
まずは 勉強だね
Coming.
（チセ）は〜い
（サイモン）ゴホッ ゴホッ…
Hey.
やあ　いつもの薬 もらえるかな
Can I have the usual medicine?
Simon-san.
サイモンさん
すぐに
Right away.
（サイモン）コホッ コホッ…
It's elderberry syrup.
（チセ）ニワトコのシロップです
Wow.
（サイモン）これは…
喉にいいから
It's good for your throat.
ありがとう
Thanks.
I just remembered, this is the
first thing Ainsworth gave me, too.
エインズワースに
初めて もらったのも
これだったなあってね
Elias did?
エリアスに？
I'm technically his supervisor, after all.
私は… まあ 一応
あいつの監視役だから
I even used to act the part.
昔は“らしい”こともしてたんだよ
But you know, with this thing being the way it is...
でも ほら ここが こうだから
（サイモン）ゴホッ ゴホッ…
Shut up.
（エリアス）うるさい
あいつは優しいよね
He's kind, isn't he?
Yup, delicious.
うん おいしい　同じ味だ
It tastes the same.
こんな時間に お客さん？
A guest? This late?
Coming.
は〜い
お待たせしました
Sorry to keep you waiting.
Is the master of the house available?
（灰の目）
屋敷の主人は ご在宅であろうか？
Ashen Eye.
灰の目！
I'd heard a rumor that a new mage was born.
（灰の目）
新しい魔法使いが生まれたと
風のうわさに聞いてな
I came to celebrate.
祝いをしたくて寄ったのだ
This man's been alive for millennia.
（エリアス）何千年と生きてる者だ
時々 交流しに来る
He comes occasionally to chat.
Be careful. He isn't human.
人間じゃあないから 気をつけて
You have no reason to be fearful of me.
（灰の目）
なに
そのように おびえるものではない
I don't intend to harm you one bit.
傷の１つも付ける気などないわ
おお… 東の果ての血の者だな
You carry the blood of the Far East.
（チセ）
砂のにおいがする
He smells of sand.
But this hair, those eyes...
（灰の目）しかし この髪 その目…
Yours aren't quite the same as those
of the inhabitants of that island nation.
あの島国の者が染まる土の色とは
いささか異なる
I believe your lineage may also carry a
tinge of blood from the western continent.
お前の祖に 大陸の西に連なる血を
持つ者がいるのだろう
（チセ）え… すみません その…
Sorry, I don't know much about my family.
家族のことは分からなくて
（灰の目）よい よい
That's fine.
血のつながりは
Bonds of blood are
insignificant in living as an individual.
個として生きるには
ささいなことよ
人間は いつも
無用に物事を考え過ぎる
Humans overthink everything.
ただただ
本質に溺れればいいものを
You ought to drown yourselves in your true nature.
Now...
さあ
我らを とらえ縛る
一族の末子(まつご)に贈り物を！
A gift for the youngest born of
those who capture and bind my people!
（エリアス）灰の目！
Ashen Eye!
（灰の目）フッフッフ…
Chise...
（エリアス）チセ…
The moon witnessed our incomplete cycles.
tsuki wa miteita kaketeru bokura
We called to one another,
tagai wo yobiai nagara
Walking distant paths as we took the long way around.
toomawari de tooi michi wo aruita
Red and black attract one another...
hikiyoseau aka to kuro ga
Shadow and light chase after one another...
oikakeau yami to hikari ga
They're made of two related things
futatsu no tsuranaru mono de tsukurareteru yo
...everything in this world is.
konoyo no subete wa
Because you're here, I'm here.
anata ga iru kara watashi wa iru
Even apart, we're side by side.
hanaretemo soba ni iru
soba ni iru
We're side by side.
Everyone is continually searching
daremo ga jibun no mou hitotsu no
For one precious thing
kataware to iu taisetsu na mono
That they can call their other half.
sagashi tsudzuketeru yo
Guided by instinct, are we brought to
a rift between humans and non-humans,
（チセ）
本能の導く先にあるもの
それは
人と 人ならざる者の間に横たわる
埋めようのない隔絶なのか
one which we can never overcome?
Humans are so foolish.
（リャナン･シー）人間って バカね
And selfish, too.
そして わがままだわ